<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section xml:id="sec-eigen-intro"
	 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

  <title> Vector Spaces </title>

  <introduction>
  <p>
    Earlier, we considered <m>\mathbb{R}^n</m>, the set of <m>n</m>-dimensional column
    vectors. We now introduce a more general concept of “vector”, as an element
    of an abstract vector space. Basically, vectors are entities that can be added
    and scaled. While some vectors look like lists of numbers (for example, column
    vectors, row vectors), other kinds of vectors don’t look like lists of numbers
    at all (for example, functions, polynomials). Part of the power of linear algebra
    comes from our ability to find vector spaces in many unexpected places.
  </p>

  <p>
    Much of the content of this chapter will be a repetition of things we have already
    seen in the context of <m>\mathbb{R}^n</m>. For example, we will be talking about
    linear combinations, linear independence, spanning sets, bases, subspaces,
    linear transformations, and so on. We initially introduced these concepts in
    the context of the vector space <m>\mathbb{R}^n</m>, so that they would be easier
    to understand. We will now see that they in fact apply to all vector spaces.
  </p>

  <section xml:id="section-definition-vector-spaces">
    <title>Definition of vector spaces</title>

    <!-- <objectives>
      <ul>
      <li>Develop the concept of a vector space through axioms.</li>
      <li>
        Use the vector space axioms to determine if a set and its operations
        constitute a vector space.
      </li>
      <li>Encounter several examples of vector spaces.</li>
      </ul>
    </objectives> -->

    <definition xml:id="definition-vector-space">
      <title>Vector space</title>

      <p>
        Let <m>K</m> be a field. A <term>vector space</term> over <m>K</m> is a set <m>V</m>
        equipped with two operations of <term>addition</term> and <term>scalar multiplication</term>, such
        that the following properties hold:
      </p>

      <ul>
        <li>
          <em>A1.</em> Commutative law of addition:
          <m>\uvec + \vvec = \vvec + \uvec</m>.
        </li>
        <li>
          <em>A2.</em> Associative law of addition:
          <m>(\uvec + \vvec) + \wvec = \uvec + (\vvec + \wvec)</m>.
        </li>
        <li>
          <em>A3.</em> The existence of an additive unit:
          there exists an element <m>\zerovec \in V</m> such that for all <m>\uvec</m>,
          <m>\uvec + \zerovec = \uvec</m>.
        </li>
        <li>
          <em>A4.</em> The law of additive inverses:
          <m>\uvec + (-\uvec) = \zerovec</m>.
        </li>
        <li>
          <em>SM1.</em> The distributive law over vector addition:
          <m>k(\uvec + \vvec) = k\uvec + k\vvec</m>.
        </li>
        <li>
          <em>SM2.</em> The distributive law over scalar addition:
          <m>(k + \ell)u = ku + \ell u</m>.
        </li>
        <li>
          <em>SM3.</em> The associative law for scalar multiplication:
          <m>k(\ell u) = (k\ell)u</m>.
        </li>
        <li>
          <em>SM4.</em> The rule for multiplication by one:
          <m>1u = u</m>.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </definition>

    <p>
      The above definition is concerned about two operations: vector addition,
      denoted by <m>v + w</m>, and scalar multiplication, denoted by <m>kv</m>
      or sometimes <m>k \cdot v</m>. In the law of additive inverses, we have
      written <m>-u</m> for <m>(-1)u</m>.
    </p>

    <p>
      Often, the scalars will be real numbers, but it is also possible to use
      scalars from a different field <m>K</m>. We also use the term
      <m>K</m>-vector space to refer to a vector space over a field <m>K</m>.
      When <m>K = \mathbb{R}</m>, we also speak of a real vector space, and when
      <m>K = \mathbb{C}</m>, we speak of a complex vector space. If the field
      is clear from the context, we often don’t mention it at all, and just speak
      of a “vector space”.
    </p>

    <p>
      The elements of a vector space are called vectors. Our first example of a
      vector space is of course <m>\mathbb{R}^n</m>.
    </p>

    <example xml:id="example-rn-vector-space">
      <title><m>\mathbb{R}^n</m> is a vector space</title>

      <statement>
        <p> The set <m>\mathbb{R}^n</m> of <m>n</m>-dimensional real column vectors,
        with the usual operations of vector addition and scalar multiplication,
        is a vector space. More generally, if <m>K</m> is a field, the set
        <m>K^n</m> of <m>n</m>-dimensional column vectors with components in
        <m>K</m> is a <m>K</m>-vector space.
        </p>

        <p>
          <b>Proof:</b> Properties (A1)–(A4) hold by our definition of vector addition, and
          properties (SM1)–(SM4) hold by our definition of vector-scalar
          multiplication.
        </p>
      </statement>
    </example>

    <example xml:id="example-p2-polynomials">
      <title>Vector space of polynomials of degree 2</title>

      <statement>
        Let <m>P_2</m> be the set of all polynomials of degree at most 2 with
        coefficients from a field <m>K</m>, i.e., expressions of the form
        <m>p(x) = ax^2 + bx + c</m>, where <m>a,b,c \in K</m>. Define addition
        and scalar multiplication of polynomials in the usual way:
        <m>
          (ax^2 + bx + c) + (a'x^2 + b'x + c') =
          (a + a')x^2 + (b + b')x + (c + c')
        </m>
        and
        <m>k(ax^2 + bx + c) = kax^2 + kbx + kc</m>.
        Then <m>P_2</m> is a vector space.
      </statement>
    </example>

  </section>

  
  <xi:include href="exercises/exercises8-1.xml" /> 

</section>

